Finding aid to Record Group 9. Photographs, of the YWCA of the U.S.A. records SSC.MS.00324.RG9
Sophia Smith Collection
- Prints and negatives, 1
  - International Work, D
    - Uganda: Health and nutrition, circa 1953-1961 (Box 1021, Folder 7)
      Uganda; Young Women's Christian associations -- Uganda; Women -- Uganda; Nutrition -- Uganda; Health education -- Uganda; Cooking -- Study and teaching -- Uganda; Children -- Uganda
    - Uganda: Program, circa 1953-1967 (Box 1021, Folder 8-9)
      Photographs of regular and special programming of young women's Christian associations in Uganda. Photographed program include activities and classes for women, children and youth including childcare and nursery, nutrition classes, recreation, dressmaking classes, meetings, family planning consultation, and travel.
      Uganda; Young Women's Christian associations -- Uganda; Women -- Uganda; Nutrition -- Uganda; Special events -- Uganda; Children -- Uganda; Adult education of women -- Uganda; Leadership in women; Women -- International cooperation; Youth -- Uganda
    - Uganda: Women at work series, circa 1950-1969 (Box 1021, Folder 10-11)
      "Women at Work" photograph series. The series is comprised of images of women engaged in work in the following roles, sales girl, airline hostess, dentist, hospital worker, radiographer, artist, accountant, dressmaker, mother, and traffic policewoman. The final photograph is an image of three women at the business training course.
      Women -- Employment -- Uganda; Uganda; Women -- Uganda; Leadership in women
    - Uganda: Y-Teens, circa 1950-1965 (Box 1022, Folder 1)
      Photographs of Y-Teen programs and members from young women's Christian associations in Uganda. Photographs include images of girls writing thank you notes to teenagers in the United States for world fellowship gifts, a group of nurse trainees, a group of girls playing games in the grass and two girls preparing for a sewing project.
      Young Women's Christian associations -- Uganda; Women -- Uganda; Uganda; Teenage girls -- Uganda
    - Uruguay, circa 1921-1977 (Box 1022, Folder 2-4)
      Photographs of young women's Christian association members, programs and activities in Uruguay. Photographed programs and activities include camps for girls, recreation, dances, conferences, nursery schools, and classes.
      Uruguay; Young Women's Christian associations -- Uruguay; Women -- Uruguay; Recreation -- Uruguay; Camps -- Uruguay; Children -- Uruguay; Child care services -- Uruguay; Leadership in women; Women -- International cooperation
    - Vietnam, 1968-1971 (Box 1022, Folder 5)
      Photographs of medical service, programs for refugees, services for orphans and United Service Organization (USO) programs in Vietnam. Many photographs are labeled with a place and person's name in pencil on the reverse and some mention the ACS, likely the Asian Christian Service.
      Viet Nam; Refugees -- Vietnam; Clinics -- Vietnam; Women -- International cooperation; Orphans -- Vietnam; Asian Christian Service; United Service Organizations (U.S.)
    - Yemen, circa 1920-1929 (Box 1022, Folder 6)
      Photograph of Princess Eudoxia of Bulgaria standing with two other women visiting the YWCA camp in Yemen.
      Young Women's Christian associations -- Yemen; Yemen
    - Zaire, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1022, Folder 7)
      Photograph of a women in what appears to be a factory. Caption on reverse of photograph reads "She. too, is a future labour inspector. The need for women officials will increase as more girls take up paid employment." The english caption is followed by french. Additional marking appear on the reverse of the photograph.
      Democratic Republic of the Congo; Women -- Employment -- Congo (Democratic Republic)
    - Zambia/Northern Rhodesia, circa 1960-1970 (Box 1022, Folder 8-9)
      Photographs of young women's Christian association programs, events, members and leaders in Zambia. Photographed programs and activities include kindergartens and other programs for young children, Y-Teen clubs and recreation, vocation and literacy classes for women, special events, opening ceremonies for a new building for the YWCA of the Copperbelt, and Buseko Home Industries Project. A series of photographs of the Botswana Regional YWCA Consultation is also included. The photographs include women from several countries in the region and it is unclear why they are included in this folder. Geographic labels on attached captions and on the reverse of photographs use both names, Northern Rhodesia and Zambia.
      Zambia; Young Women's Christian associations -- Zambia; Women -- Zambia; Teenage girls -- Zambia; Women -- International cooperation; Recreation -- Zambia; Leadership in women; Children -- Zambia
    - Zimbabwe/Rhodesia/Southern Rhodesia, circa 1960-1987 (Box 1022, Folder 10-12)
      Photographs of young women's Christian association programs, leaders, buildings, members, and activities in Zimbabwe. Photographed program activities include English language classes, Y-Teen clubs, childcare, and nurseries. Conferences and special events include the first All Africa Conference, a leadership training conference, the All Africa Youth Conference, and building openings and groundbreakings. Attached captions and markings on photographs use the geographic terms Rhodesia, Zimbabwe, and Southern Rhodesia.
      Zimbabwe; Young Women's Christian associations -- Zimbabwe; Women -- Zimbabwe; Children -- Zimbabwe; Teenage girls -- Zimbabwe; Adult education of women -- Zimbabwe; Congresses and conventions -- Zimbabwe; Leadership in women; Women -- International cooperation
  - Program, E
    - Advocacy: Public affairs, circa 1961-1984 (Box 1023, Folder 1)
      Public affairs programs and activities in the YWCA of the U.S.A. seek to educate members on important social, economic, and political issues in addition to facilitating actionable programs. Through the public affairs committee the YWCA of the U.S.A. developed a program of emphasis, released statements of position, collaborated with other organizations and supported members in partaking in advocacy. Photographed activities include a tutoring program sponsored by the public affairs committee, women engaged in political activity, YWCA Peace Network displays, voter registration programs, and additional public affairs activities from several local associations.
      Leadership in women; Women -- Political activity; Voter registration; Tutors and tutoring; YWCA of the U.S.A. Public Affairs Committee
    - Advocacy: Demonstrations, parades, and protests, circa 1961-1996 (Box 1023, Folder 2-5)
      As part of their activities to work towards social, economic, and racial justice for all, the YWCA of the USA and its members participated in national and local demonstrations to raise awareness for issues important to the organization and its members. Photographed demonstrations include national events such as the 1963 March on Washington, the 1992 March for Women's Lives, and 1968 Solidarity day. Other marches and demonstrations address issues such as the Equal Rights Amendment (ERA), peace and disarmament, abortion and reproductive rights, hunger, and violence against women. While the majority of the photographs are of protests, marches and demonstrations, there are also several photographs of the 1983 Rose Parade.
      Leadership in women; Equal rights amendments; Women and peace; Disarmament -- Peace; Racism -- United States; Abortion -- Political aspects; March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom (1963: Washington, D.C.); Demonstrations; Women political activists; Civil rights demonstrations; Reproductive rights activists
    - Advocacy: Institute for public leadership, circa 1980-1989 (Box 1023, Folder 6)
      Contact sheets and participant portraits from a YWCA of the U.S.A. institute for public leadership.
      Leadership in women
    - Advocacy: contact sheet, Emily's List luncheon during Inaugural Week, 1993 Personnel and Training: American Committee, Secretaries' Training Institute, fall term 1904 (Box 1050, Folder 1)
    - Personnel and training: General, circa 1935-1985 (Box 1023, Folder 7)
      Photographs of YWCA of the U.S.A. training programs for leaders and staff. Included are photographs from training courses held at Oberlin College, "Training A" in Houston, Texas, and other regional or national training programs.
      Leadership in women; Employees -- Training of
    - Personnel and training: Secretaries' Training Institute, 1898; 1904 (Box 1023, Folder 8)
      Group photographs from the Secretarial Training Institute of the American Committee of Young Women's Christian Associations, a predecessor organization to the YWCA of the U.S.A.
      Leadership in women; Employees -- Training of; American Committee of Young Women's Christian Associations
    - Personnel and training: National Training School, circa 1909-1925 (Box 1023, Folder 9-11)
      Photographs of classes and participants of the YWCA of the U.S.A. National Training School. The school, located at 3 Grammercy Park and then 135 West 52nd Street, New York, offered courses for YWCA leaders, potential leaders, and women interested in Christian group work. Courses included history of the YWCA, religion, organization and administration, church history, and "the application of Christianity to present day problems." Group photographs from each location are followed by a series of "snapshots" taken at the schools as well as at vacation cottages.
      National Training School photographs are arranged into the following folders:
      3 Gramercy Park, New York City
      135 West 52nd St., New York City
      Snapshots
    - Personnel and training: School for Professional Workers, circa 1951-1964 (Box 1023, Folder 12-14)
      YWCA schools for professional workers were regional institutes for new or experienced YWCA of the USA staff offering training in the YWCA of the USA, social issues, and Christianity. Photographs include class photos in addition to photographs of instruction and program activities.
    - Personnel and training: National YWCA Program Institute for Executive Directors and Program Directors, 1966 (Box 1023, Folder 15)
      Photographs of the YWCA of the U.S.A. National Program Institute for Executive Directors and Program Directors held at the University of Chicago.
      Leadership in women; Employees -- Training of; Chicago, Cook, Illinois, United States
    - Personnel and training: Public Policy Forum, Empowerment Through Public Policy, May 1990 (Box 1023, Folder 16)
      Photographs from the YWCA of the U.S.A. Public Policy Forum: Empowerment Through Public Policy.
    - Employed women, circa 1896-1989 (Box 1024, Folder 1)
      Photographs of YWCA of the USA employment training programs as well as photographs of employed women performing duties. Many of the photographs, especially early one feature secretarial training or women employed as secretaries. Additional photographs include nurses and nurses training and vocational guidance services. Photographs also include a series of photographs of Kay Crowley, an engineering aide at an aircraft factory during World War II.
      Women -- Employment; Secretaries; Vocational guidance; Occupational training
    - Employed women: Clubs, circa 1905-1931 (Box 1024, Folder 2)
      Group photographs of YWCA clubs for women employed in industry. Most photograph have simple identifying information on the reverse such as place or club name.
      Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers
    - Employed women: Conferences, circa 1908-1951 (Box 1024, Folder 3)
      Photographs from regional YWCA of the USA conferences for women employed in industry or business including group photographs. Many conferences were held at camp grounds or similar recreation facitlities and photographs include images of women participating in outdoor recreation.
      Women -- Employment; Women blue collar workers; Women -- Employment -- Congresses; Outdoor recreation
    - Employed women: Business Office Culture Project, 1968-1970 (Box 1024, Folder 4-5)
      The Business Office Culture Project was a special project of the National Board of the YWCA of the USA in cooperation with the United States Department of Labor to provide women age 17-25 with training in office skills and culture to increase their confidence and employability. Classes included training in speech, poise, typing, math, mimeograph, punch cards, and job interviews. Participating clubs were located in Dallas, Texas, Mt. Vernon, New York, St. Louis, Missouri, Tacoma, Washington, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, and Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania.
      Business Office Culture Project photographs are arranged into the following folders:
      Dallas, Mt. Vernon, St. Louis, Tacoma
      Philadelphia, Pittsburgh
      Women -- Employment; Vocational guidance; Adult education of women; Secretaries
    - Employed women: Job Corps-YWCA Extension Residence Program, 1967-1975 (Box 1024, Folder 6-7, Box 1025, Folder 1-11)
      YWCA Job Corps was a program that provided lodging, basic education and job training for young women in need. The program was part of an initiative launched by the United States Department of Labor and the Economic Security Act. The YWCA of the USA program utilized its existing structure and expertise to train Job Corps members and provide basic education for the completion of high school equivalency exams, access to health care and counseling, and instruction in life skills through shared living responsibilities. Photographed job skills training include typing, dental assistance, medical assistant, military, office skills, and teacher's aide. In addition to their job skills training and development, YWCA Job Corps women were encouraged to develop personal interests and given opportunity for recreation. Photographed recreation activities include physical fitness, horseback riding, and swimming and include a photograph of Jack La Lanne demonstrating donated fitness equipment to "Miss Job Corps" Lanetta Madden.
      Job Corps-YWCA Extension Residence Program photographs are arranged into the following folders:
      Awards
      Buildings
      Classes, personal development
      Conferences
      Counseling
      Graduations
      Graduates, groups
      Groups, snapshots
      Job skills training
      Staff, leaders, and speakers
      Recreation
      Miscellaneous
      Women -- Employment; Adult education of women; Vocational guidance; Women -- Employment -- Congresses; Women--Counseling of; Commencement ceremonies; Leadership in women; Outdoor recreation; Physical fitness for women; Recreation
    - Employed women: Mill villages work, circa 1900-1919 (Box 1025, Folder 12)
      The YWCA of the USA and its associations conducted work at mill villages providing services, recreation, and clubs to women and their families living and working in mill villages. Photographs include images of women working in mills, mill village housing and camps, a secretary's house, and club programs. Photographed activities include recreation programs for children and adults, classes, and celebrations.
      Mills and mill-work; Women -- Employment; Outdoor recreation; Recreation; Industrial housing
    - Employed women: Non-Traditional Jobs for Women training programs, circa 1970-1979 (Box 1025, Folder 13-14)
      Non-traditional jobs for women training projects provided skills training, counseling, and placement services for women entering into trades. Photographs include images of women engaged in learning and work including trades such as mechanics, machine operating, electronics and wiring, carpentry, building trades, plumbing, and telephone line work.
      Women -- Employment; Vocational guidance; Women blue collar workers; Women construction workers
    - Altamont Industrial Conference, 1920 (Box 1050)
    - We-go-u-go Industrial Club of the Denver YWCA: photo album/scrapbook, 1923-25 (Box 1052A)
    - Immigration and foreign communities, circa 1910-1979 (Box 1026, Folder 1-3)
      YWCA of the USA's work with immigrant women and their families include offering classes, services, and community relations. Early work centered in international institutes, branches of local associations focused on meeting the needs of the immigrant community. Photographs include images of services and programs, members, buildings, and women demonstrating traditional dress from their home countries.
      Immigration and foreign communities photographs are arranged into the following folders:
      International Institutes
      Women immigrants; Social work with immigrants; Traditional dress; Children of immigrants
    - Race and racial justice: American Indian work, circa 1910-1993 (Box 1026, Folder 4)
      Photographs highlighting the YWCA of the USA's work with Native American women. Photographs include images from the Native American Caucus at the 1977 National Women's Conference in Houston Texas, snapshots of National Board member Deanna Espina during inauguration week 1993, and unidentified photographs of Native American services and participants.
      Native American women; Espina, Deanna Ruth, 1939-2012
    - Race and racial justice: Early photographs, circa 1910-1926 (Box 1026, Folder 5)
      Photographs of the YWCA of the USA's early work with African American women and girls including images of conference attendees, student work conferences, leaders, Girl Reserves, and hostess houses.
      African American women -- Societies and clubs; World War, 1914-1918 -- Participation, African American; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Young Women's Christian associations; African American women
    - Race and racial justice: Miscellaneous activities and groups, circa 1960-1998 (Box 1026, Folder 6)
      Photographs depicting the YWCA of the USA's leaders, programs, and conferences working towards the elimination of racism and the empowerment of black women including the Institute for Leadership in Intergroup Relations, Action Audit for Change workshop, acceptance ceremony for the Becky Cain Award for Vision, and Solidarity Day march.
      African American women; Racism -- United States; Race relations; Civil rights demonstrations
    - Race and racial justice: National Convocation on Racial Justice, 1972 June 15 (Box 1026, Folder 7)
      Photographs and speaker portraits from the 1972 YWCA of the USA National Convocation on Racial Justice.
      Racism -- United States; Anti-racism; Women -- Congresses; Race relations
    - Race and racial justice: Racial Justice Convocation, 1990 February (Box 1026, Folder 8)
      Photographs from the YWCA of the USA Racial Justice Convocation.
      Anti-racism; Women -- Congresses; Race relations; Social justice
    - Race and racial justice: Racism: A Woman's Agenda roundtable, 1989 (Box 1026, Folder 9)
      Photographs of the roundtable "Racism: A Woman's Agenda," a discussion centered on the effects of racism from the perspective of women and cosponsored by the YWCA of the USA and Ladies' Home Journal.
      Racism -- United States; Anti-racism; Leadership in women; Social justice; Ladies' Home Journal
    - Race and racial justice: Community associations, circa 1970-1976 (Box 1026, Folder 10)
      Photographs highlighting the work of local YWCA of the USA in implementing programs combating racism, celebrating African American heritage, and increasing positive race relations. Photographs include events centered around the YWCA of the USA One Imperative, or Elimination of Racism efforts, dialogue groups, action audits, receptions, and courses. Most photographs are identified on the reverse.
      African American women; Anti-racism; Race relations; Social justice
    - Teen Age and Younger Girls
      - Teenage and younger girls, circa 1910-1999 (Box 1026, Folder 11-13)
        The YWCA of the USA's work with teenagers began with Girl Reserve clubs which later became the Y-Teen program. Photographs include portraits of members and program participants and photographs of program activities such as conferences, program planning, recreation, and meetings.
        Teenage girls; Teenage girls -- Societies and clubs; Leadership in adolescents; Recreation; Youth movements; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. G.R. Dept.; YWCA of the U.S.A. Teen-age Department
      - National Teen Council/National Teen Organization, circa 1972-1993 (Box 1026, Folder 14)
        Photographs of YWCA of the USA National Teen Organization NTO) and National Teen Council (NTC) meetings and conferences.
        Leadership in adolescents; Teenage girls; Teenage girls -- Societies and clubs; YWCA of the U.S.A. Teen-age Department
      - Babysitter publicity series, circa 1960-1969 (Box 1026, Folder 15)
        Photographs demonstrating babysitting and childcare methods.
        Leadership in adolescents; Teenage girls; Babysitting; YWCA of the U.S.A. Teen-age Department
      - Eight Week Clubs, circa 1910-1919 (Box 1026, Folder 16)
        Photographs of YWCA of the USA Girl Reserve Eight Week Clubs. Most are group photographs with clubs identified on the back of the photographs.
        Teenage girls; Teenage girls -- Societies and clubs; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. G.R. Dept.
      - International YWCA clubs for teenage girls, undated (Box 1026, Folder 17)
        Photographs of Girl Reserve clubs and YWCA clubs for teenage girls from around the world. All photographs are captioned.
        Teenage girls -- Latvia; Teenage girls -- Lebanon; Teenage girls -- China -- Hong Kong; Youth -- China; Teenage girls -- Japan; Teenage girls -- Brazil; Teenage girls -- Philippines; Teenage girls -- Hawaii; Youth -- International cooperation; Teenage girls -- Societies and clubs; Youth movements
      - Younger girls and Girl Reserve regional conferences, circa 1913-1945 (Box 1027, Folder 1-3)
        Photographs of YWCA of the USA regional conferences for younger girls and Girl Reserves including posed group photographs and candid photographs of conference programs and activities. Many of these conferences were held at camp facilities and included recreation as part of their program in addition to conference sessions.
        Teenage girls; Teenage girls -- Societies and clubs; Youth movements; Leadership in adolescents; Outdoor recreation; Congresses and conventions; Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A. G.R. Dept.
      - Y-Teens regional and national conferences, circa 1953-1998 (Box 1027, Folder 4-7)
        Photographs of participants, leaders, sessions, and activities from regional and national YWCA of the USA Y-Teen conferences.
        Teenage girls; Teenage girls -- Societies and clubs; Youth movements; Leadership in adolescents; Congresses and conventions; Recreation; Outdoor recreation; YWCA of the U.S.A. Teen-age Department
      - YMCA-YWCA National Conference for High School Youth, 1947 (Box 1027, Folder 8-9)
        Photographs from the join YMCA/YWCA conference for high school youth held at Grinnell College. Photographs include images of delegates participating in program planning, conferences sessions, and social activities.
        Teenage girls; Teenage boys; Youth movements; Congresses and conventions; Leadership in adolescents; Grinnell, Poweshiek, Iowa, United States; YMCA of the USA; YWCA of the U.S.A. Teen-age Department
      - First National Y-Teen Conference, 1956 November (Box 1027, Folder 10-13)
        The First National Y-Teen Conference brought together Y-Teens from across the country to develop their leadership skills, participate in the larger YWCA movement, and learn from their peers and adult leaders. Photographs include conference ceremonials at the National Cathedral, conference sessions, a numbered series of photographs with index, and group photographs.
        First National Y-Teen Conference photographs are arranged as follows: